Dairy Science
中間[ちゅうかん]:middle/midway/interim, 中間[ちゅうげん]:samurai's attendant/footman, 考査[こうさ]:examination/consideration/test, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
この前の中間考査返すぞ
I'll now return your midterms.
In my self-assessments,
自己[じこ]:self/oneself, 採点[さいてん]:marking/grading/scoring, 各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), 教科[きょうか]:subject/curriculum
自己採点では各教科ともミスは１つか２つ
I only missed one or
two in each subject.
I'll be the top student overall
among this lot for sure.
総合[そうごう]:synthesis/coordination|comprehensive, 位[くらい]:throne|government position|social standing||, 位[い]:rank|decimal place|counter for ghosts, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman)
こいつらの中なら総合１位は間違いない
Next, Hachiken!
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order
次　八軒
Yes!
はい
Name:
Hachiken Yuugo
個[こ, コ]:counter for articles|counter for military units|individual, 個[か, カ]:counter for the ichi-ni-san counting system (usu. directly preceding the item being counted)/a noun read using its on-yomi, ミスる:to make a mistake/to mess up/to make an error
チクショー　１個ミスった
Dammit, I made a mistake...
Wow, Hachiken!
すげえ:incredible/unbelievable, じゃん:isn't it
おっ　すげえじゃん　八軒
農家[のうか]:farmer/farming family|farmhouse, 畜産[ちくさん]:animal husbandry, 点数[てんすう]:marks/points/score, すげえ:incredible/unbelievable
農家じゃねえのに畜産でその点数はすげえよ
That's an impressive livestock score,
considering you're not from a farm.
Nah, it's nothing—
いやあ　それほどでも…
Livestock Science
(Graph from left to right)
Crop Science
Agricultural Machinery
Agribusiness Management
Biotechnology
Food Manufacturing
Information Management
Japanese
Math
Chemistry
Crop Science
Food Manufacturing
Agribusiness Management
Hachiken Yuugo
すげえ:incredible/unbelievable
おー　すげえ
Oh, wow.
Hachiken, you're on top!
You totally crushed everyone.
Midterm Results
ぶっちぎり:establishing a large lead over one's competitors/breaking away (from the field), 総合[そうごう]:synthesis/coordination|comprehensive, 位[くらい]:throne|government position|social standing||, 位[い]:rank|decimal place|counter for ghosts, じゃん:isn't it
八軒ぶっちぎりで総合１位じゃん
釈然とする[しゃくぜんとする]:to be fully satisfied with (e.g. an explanation or apology)
釈然としない！
I'm not satisfied!
本格的[ほんかくてき]:genuine|full-scale|full-fledged, 夏[なつ]:summer, 夏[か]:Xia (dynasty of China; perhaps mythological), 日差し[ひざし]:sunlight/rays of the sun
本格的な夏の日差しが
肌[はだ, はだえ]:skin|body (in the context of intimate bodily contact)|surface|, 焦がす[こがす]:to burn/to scorch/to singe, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
肌を焦がしていく様に
恋焦がれる[こいこがれる]:to yearn for/to pine/to be deeply in love with
私もあなたに恋焦がれる
海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, ドライブ:drive/trip by car/driving, 運転[うんてん]:operation (of a machine, etc.)|driving|working (capital, etc.)
海へドライブ 運転するよ
横顔[よこがお]:face in profile/profile/face seen from the side, 撫でる[なでる]:to stroke/to caress|to comb (hair), 潮風[しおかぜ]:salty sea breeze/salt wind, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
横顔撫でる 潮風が気持ちいいsummer day
la la la summer day
ビーチパラソル:beach parasol/beach umbrella, カラフル:colorful/colourful
ビーチパラソルカラフルだ yeah
砂浜[すなはま]:sandy beach, 咲く[さく]:to bloom, 花[はな]:flower|cherry blossom|beauty||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
砂浜に咲く　花みたい
KISS YOU あなたの心
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 感ずる[かんずる]:to feel/to sense
もっともっと近くにいたい　感じたい
私だけ見て
膨らむ[ふくらむ]:to expand/to swell (out)/to get big
KISS YOU ぐっと膨らんだ
胸[むね, むな]:chest|breasts|heart||, 思い[おもい]:thought|imagination|desire||, 唇[くちびる]:lips, のせる:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride/to give a lift, 伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
胸の思い　唇にのせて　伝えたいと
だから　KISS YOU
だから　さあ　KISS YOU
Episode 4
Hachiken
Bakes Pizza
Good job!
疲れ[つかれ]:tiredness/fatigue
お疲れ
Good work, everyone.
お疲れさま[おつかれさま]:thank you/many thanks|that's enough for today
お疲れさまでーす
Good job!
疲れ[つかれ]:tiredness/fatigue
お疲れ
Oh, here they come.
連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe
おっ　連中きてるな
春[はる]:spring|New Year|prime (of one's life, etc.)||, 終わり[おわり]:the end, 感ずる[かんずる]:to feel/to sense
これ見ると春も終わりって感じよねー
Seeing them makes me feel
that spring's coming to an end.
下半身[かはんしん, しもはんしん]:lower half of body, 筋肉痛[きんにくつう]:muscular pain/myalgia
下半身　筋肉痛
Lower body muscle pain.
乗り[のり, ノリ]:riding|spread (of paints)|-seater (e.g. two-seater)|, 始め[はじめ]:beginning|first (in line, etc.)|origin|
乗り始めのころはみんなそうなるの
Everyone gets that
when they start horseback riding.
通過[つうか]:passage through (e.g. train skipping a station)/transit|passing (e.g. exam, bill through parliament), 儀礼[ぎれい]:etiquette/courtesy, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
通過儀礼みたいなものよ
It's like a rite of passage.
どうすればいいのでしょうか
What should I... do...
Endure.
耐える[たえる]:to bear|to support|to be fit for
耐えて
どける:to put something out of the way/to move (something, someone) aside|to remove
どけどけー　ひくぞー
Outta the way!
Coming through.
あっ　西川
Nishikawa!
トラクター:tractor
何だ　これ　トラクター部？
What's this? The tractor club?
No such thing.
んな部ねえよ
実習[じっしゅう]:practice/practising/training (esp. practical and hands-on), 返し[かえし]:reversal|return gift|barb (on a fishing hook)|
実習で使ったの　返しに来たんだよ
I just came to return
what we used in practicum.
免許[めんきょ]:license/permit/licence, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
つーかお前免許持ってんの
Wait, do you have a license?
私有地[しゆうち]:demesne/estate/private land, 要る[いる]:to need/to want
私有地なら要らないんだぜ
Don't need one to drive
on private property.
実家[じっか]:(one's parents') home, ばりばり:tearing/ripping|crunching, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
それに　俺　実家でばりばり乗ってたし
Besides, I was drove them
all the time at home.
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures
ちょうどよかった
Good timing.
馬術[ばじゅつ]:horse-riding/horsemanship/equestrian art, 寝[ね, しん]:sleep, 寝[ぬ]:to lie down/to go to bed/to go to sleep, 運ぶ[はこぶ]:to carry|to come|to wield (a tool, etc.)|, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
君　馬術部に寝わらを運んでもらえませんか
Can you bring some bedding straw
to the equestrian club?
Sure thing.
いいっすよ
Wanna ride?
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
乗るか
Wow, this is so high!
高[たか, だか]:quantity/amount/volume, 高[こう]:high school|high-
高え　ロボみてー
It's like a robot!
It's got a four-cylinder diesel engine
with a turbo intercooler!
気筒[きとう]:cylinder, ディーゼル:diesel, ターボ:turbo, エンジン:engine, 搭載[とうさい]:loading (on board)/equipping|equipped (with)
４気筒ディーゼルターボ　インタークーラーエンジン搭載
The all-wheel drive T-8000!
四[し, よん]:four, 四[スー]:four, 輪[りん]:counter for wheels and flowers, 輪[わ]:ring|hoop|wheel|, 駆動[くどう]:driving force
四輪駆動Ｔ８０００
It's got the standard package:
Supercreep speeds, Speedmatching, and AutoDrive!
スーパー:super, クリープ:creep, 速[そく]:gear/speed (e.g. 4-speed transmission), スピード:speed, マッチング:matching, モード:mode (musical mode, mode of probability distribution, state of physical system)
スーパークリープ速　スピードマッチングモード
オート:auto/automobile/automatic, ドライブ:drive/trip by car/driving, モード:mode (musical mode, mode of probability distribution, state of physical system), 標準[ひょうじゅん]:standard/level/norm, 装備[そうび]:equipment
オートドライブモード標準装備
呪文[じゅもん]:spell/charm/incantation
呪文かよ
Are you speaking in code?
A T-series front loader
with a bale grab!
シリーズ:series, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, フロント:front (aspect, weather, war-front, etc.), ローダー:loader
Ｔシリーズ用フロントローダー
ロール:roll, グラブ:glove (esp. sports)/mitt, 仕様[しよう]:way/method|(technical) specification
ロールグラブ仕様
最大[さいだい]:biggest/greatest/largest, 持ち上げる[もちあげる]:to elevate/to raise|to flatter, 重量[じゅうりょう]:weight|heavyweight boxer
最大持ち上げ重量１，９００ｋｇ
Its maximum lift load is 1900 kilos!
パワー:power
見よ　このパワー
Observe its power!
最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate
最高速度３３キロ
Its maximum speed is 33 kph!
That's slow!
遅っ
What're they doing?
何やってんだ　あいつら
I see.
寝[ね, しん]:sleep, 寝[ぬ]:to lie down/to go to bed/to go to sleep, 学校[がっこう]:school, 取れる[とれる]:to come off|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear|to be caught||
そっか　寝わらって学校で取れたやつ使ってたんだ
So we use straw
from here for the bedding.
Of course.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally
もちろんです
餌[えさ, え]:(animal) feed/fodder|bait, 飼い葉[かいば]:fodder, 燕麦[えんばく, からすむぎ]:wild oat (Avena fatua)/wild oats|oat (Avena sativa), 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 産[うぶ]:innocent/naive|birth-, 産[さん]:(giving) birth|native of|assets
餌の飼い葉や燕麦なども全てエゾノー産ですよ
The same goes for the fodder and oats.
They're all grown here at Ezonoo.
学校[がっこう]:school, 作物[さくぶつ]:literary work, 作物[さくもつ]:produce (e.g. agricultural)/crops, 畜産[ちくさん]:animal husbandry, 食品[しょくひん]:food/food products/foodstuffs, 加工[かこう]:manufacturing/processing/treatment, 林業[りんぎょう]:forestry, 土木[どぼく]:engineering works/civil engineering/public works, 揃う[そろう]:to become complete|to be equal|to gather
この学校は作物　畜産　食品加工　林業　土木と揃っています
This school encompasses crops, livestock,
food processing, forestry, and civil engineering.
学校[がっこう]:school, 丸ごと[まるごと]:in its entirety/whole/wholly, 自給自足[じきゅうじそく]:self-sufficiency, 可能[かのう]:potential/possible/practicable
学校丸ごと自給自足が可能ですよ
It can be entirely self-sufficient.
If you guys have something
you want to make or try,
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
君たちも作りたいものややりたいことがあったら
農場[のうじょう]:farm (agriculture), 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 相談[そうだん]:consultation/discussion, なさる:to do
農場の先生に相談してみなさい
feel free to consult
one of the teachers.
They'll let you try most things.
大抵[たいてい]:mostly|probably|most||, 挑戦[ちょうせん]:challenge/defiance/dare
大抵のことは挑戦させてくれますよ
Really?!
マジっすか
I want to dismantle farm
equipment and make a robot!
農機具[のうきぐ]:agricultural machinery and equipment, ロボット:robot, 造る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
俺　農機具バラしてロボット造りてー
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular
それはさすがに怒られるだろ
I'm sure that'll get you scolded.
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, トラクター:tractor, メーカー:manufacturer/maker, 戦車[せんしゃ]:tank (military vehicle)|chariot, 造る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
昔はトラクターメーカーが戦車造ってたんだぜ
Tractor manufacturers
used to make tanks.
ロボット:robot
ロボットの１つや２つ
A robot or two shouldn't be a problem!
農業[のうぎょう]:agriculture, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
農業と関係ねえし
It's got nothing to do with agriculture!
Then a power suit for farm work!
農作業[のうさぎょう]:farmwork, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, スーツ:suit
じゃあ　農作業用パワードスーツ
ぽんぽん:pompon/pompons|tummy, 出てくる[でてくる]:to come out/to appear/to turn up
お前　やりたいことぽんぽん出てくるなぁ
You're full of ideas for
what you want to do.
うらやましい:envious (feeling, etc.)/jealous|enviable (position, etc.)
うらやましいよ
I'm jealous.
そうか
Really?
学年[がくねん]:academic year/school year|year in school, トップ:top, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, うらやましい:envious (feeling, etc.)/jealous|enviable (position, etc.)
学年トップ取る方がうらやましいけどな
I'm more jealous of someone
who can be the top student.
Come to think of it, why aren't
I that happy about it?
番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||, あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence)
そういや　俺　１番取ったのにあんまり…
All right, everyone!
諸君[しょくん]:you (people)|gentlemen/ladies and gentlemen
さて　諸君
中間[ちゅうかん]:middle/midway/interim, 中間[ちゅうげん]:samurai's attendant/footman, 考査[こうさ]:examination/consideration/test, 終わり[おわり]:the end, 天気[てんき]:weather/the elements|fair weather, 恵まれる[めぐまれる]:to be blessed with/to be rich in/to abound in
中間考査も終わり　いい天気に恵まれたので
Now that the midterms are over
and we've got good weather...
We'll be doing campus cleanup today!
本日[ほんじつ]:today, 校内[こうない]:within a school, 拾い[じゅう, とお]:ten
本日は校内のごみ拾いです
'Kay!
へ～い
ちなみ:association/link|pledge (esp. for marriage), 校内[こうない]:within a school
あの…ちなみに校内って…
Um, and when you say, "campus"...
I mean the campus!
校内[こうない]:within a school
校内です
Don't worry, it'll be fine!
大丈夫　大丈夫
当たり[あたり]:hit|success|guess||, ほんの:mere/only/just
１人当たりほんの１ｈａちょっとだから
Only about one hectare
per person, give or take!
Once you're done, we'll have
a mutton barbecue party!
拾い[じゅう, とお]:ten, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
ごみ拾いが終わったらジンギスカンパーティーですよ
Yeah!
よっしゃー:gotcha/alrighty/got it
よっしゃー！
Mutton barbecue!
ジンギスカン:Japanese mutton and vegetable dish/slotted dome cast iron grill for preparing this dish
ジンギスカン！
いや　しかし…
Man, it's endless.
出るわ　出るわ
高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, 土地[とち, どおじ]:plot of land/lot|locality
高校の土地を何だと思って…
No respect for high school property...
Whoa!
A-Are you all right?!
大丈夫ですか
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
痛てて…
O-Oww...
カーネル:kernel
カーネル！？
Colonel?!
What's this?
何だ　これ
Ooezo Agricultural High School Dormitory for Future Agriculture Managers
Here! This is it!
あった　これだ
Make a Brick Oven
I guess it's an oven?
要する[ようする]:to need/to demand/to take, オーブン:oven
要するにオーブンか
What?
何だ　石窯？
A brick oven?
埋もれる[うもれる, うずもれる]:to be buried/to be covered/to be hidden
うん　ごみに埋もれてたやつ
Yeah, it was buried in trash.
Let's Enjoy Brick Oven Cooking!!
いろんな:various, 焼ける[やける]:to burn/to be roasted|to be jealous
いろんなものが焼けるんだなぁ
I guess you can bake a lot of things.
Bread, meat...
肉[にく, しし]:flesh|meat|the physical body (as opposed to the spirit)||
パン　肉　ピザ
Pizza.
What?
P-Pizza?!
ピ…ピザ～！
聞き[きき]:hearing|rumour|tasting (alcohol, tea, etc.)
それは聞き捨てならねえ
We can't pass up that opportunity!
Can we make one?
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
作れんの
I want to eat pizza!
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
食いてー
宅配[たくはい]:home delivery, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
宅配でいつでも食えるだろ
You can get it delivered anytime, right?
We live outside of the delivery area!
宅配[たくはい]:home delivery, 圏[けん]:sphere/circle|category (only in the context of "category theory"), 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|
うち宅配圏外
Me, too!
うちも　うちも
We don't even get cell signals.
携帯[けいたい, ケイタイ]:something carried (in the hand)/handheld|mobile telephone, 電波[でんぱ, デムパ]:electromagnetic wave/radio wave|saying strange things, 届く[とどく]:to reach|to be attentive|to be delivered
うち携帯電波も届かねえし
We get the evening newspaper
the following afternoon!
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 夕刊[ゆうかん]:evening paper, 翌日[よくじつ]:next day, 昼[ひる]:noon|daytime|lunch
うちなんて夕刊が翌日の昼に来る
Seriously, delivery inequality?!
デリバリー:delivery, 格差[かくさ]:qualitative difference/disparity
デリバリー格差
ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
聞いたことがある
I heard that in cities,
you can phone in an order
都会[とかい]:city|Tokyo Metropolitan Assembly, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), 注文[ちゅうもん]:order/request, 注文[ちゅうぶん]:annotation/explanatory note, 届く[とどく]:to reach|to be attentive|to be delivered
都会では電話で注文すると３０分でピザが届くという
and get a pizza delivered
within 30 minutes.
Seriously, Beppu?!
何　本当か　別府
I've eaten frozen pizza
on Christmas day.
冷凍[れいとう]:freezing/cold storage/refrigeration, クリスマス:Christmas, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
冷凍ピザならクリスマスに食べたことあるけど
Man, I'd love to eat an actual pizza.
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
ちゃんとしたピザ食ってみてー
Maybe we can make one
since there's an oven?
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
石窯あるなら作れるんじゃないか
Well, I mean...
材料[ざいりょう]:ingredients|material (for a novel, experiment, etc.)|basis (for a decision)|
いや…ピザの材料って
You only need dough, cheese,
小麦[こむぎ]:wheat, 生地[きじ]:cloth|one's true character|unglazed pottery|, 生地[せいち]:birthplace, チーズ:cheese, 野菜[やさい]:vegetable, 肉[にく, しし]:flesh|meat|the physical body (as opposed to the spirit)||, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
小麦生地とチーズと野菜と肉くらいだろ
vegetables, and meat
for ingredients, right?
簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief
簡単じゃねえの
Isn't it easy?
任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
よし　八軒に任せた　ピザ作ってくれ
Okay, we're counting on you, Hachiken!
Please make pizza!
Huh?!
簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief
簡単なんだろ
It's easy, right?
We'll help you!
協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration
俺たちも協力するからさ
It's decided, then!
決まり[きまり]:rule|settlement|habit||
決まりだな
Yay!
イェ～イ！
ちょ…ちょっと待て
W-Wait a minute!
だいたい:outline/main point|general, だいたい:battalion, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
だいたいピザ食いたいってだけで
The school'd never let us
do this in the first place,
just because we want to eat pizza!
学校[がっこう]:school, 勝手[かって]:one's own convenience|surroundings|convenience||, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
学校が勝手なこと許すわけないだろ
It'll be fine.
大丈夫だって
バレる:to leak out (a secret)/to be exposed (a lie, improper behaviour, etc.) (behavior), みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 優等生[ゆうとうせい]:honor student/honours student, ちょこっと:rather/a little/small, 怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
バレても八軒みたいな優等生なら　ちょこっと怒られて終わるべ
Even if they find out,
a star pupil like you
would only get a minor scolding.
It's just going to be me?
俺だけかよ
But you're the only one who knows what
pizza's supposed to taste like...
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 味[あじ]:flavor|charm|experience|, 味[み]:(sense of) taste|counter for food, drink, medicine, etc.
ちゃんとしたピザの味知ってるのお前だけなんだよ
Maybe, but...
たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
そんなこと言ったって…
食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
ピザ食べたいね
Pizza sounds really good.
Yeah, it does.
うん　そうだねー
いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
やらせていただきます
I will do it.
This Saturday, then.
今週[こんしゅう]:this week, 土曜[どよう]:Saturday
じゃあ　今週の土曜な
What?!
It'll be fine!
大丈夫　大丈夫
It's only Monday.
月曜[げつよう]:Monday
まだ月曜なんだから
I said I'd do it, but...
とはいったものの…
Specialized tools?
専用[せんよう]:exclusive use/personal use|private (e.g. network), 道具[どうぐ]:tool/implement|means, 手入れ[ていれ]:care/looking after|(police) raid
専用の道具？石窯の手入れ？
Oven maintenance?
小麦粉[こむぎこ]:wheat flour, 種類[しゅるい]:variety/kind|counter for different sorts of things, 生地[きじ]:cloth|one's true character|unglazed pottery|, 生地[せいち]:birthplace, 発酵[はっこう]:fermentation/zymosis
小麦粉２種類？生地を発酵？
Two types of flour? Dough fermentation?
Mozzarella?
モッツァレラチーズ:mozzarella (cheese)
モッツァレラチーズ？
How much is all this gonna cost?
いったい:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")/...in the world (e.g. "why in the world?")|one object, いったい:region/zone/whole place, 幾ら[いくら]:how much?/how many?|even, かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
いったい幾らかかるんだ　これ
Pig Pen
Hachiken-kun's going to make pizza?
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
八軒君　ピザ作るんだって？
本当
Really?
すげえ:incredible/unbelievable, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
何かすげえ研究してるみたいだぜ
He's apparently doing a bunch
of research on the whole thing.
It'll happen this Saturday.
今週[こんしゅう]:this week, 土曜[どよう]:Saturday
今週の土曜だってよ
楽しみにする[たのしみにする]:to look forward to something
八軒　楽しみにしてるぞ
Hachiken, I'm looking forward to it!
ヤベえ　どうしよう
Damn... What should I do?
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
できないなら早く言わないと
If I can't make it happen,
I should speak up.
ベーコン:bacon, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
そういや　ベーコンも必要
Come to think of it,
I need bacon, too...
ごめんよぉぉ
Sorry!
Do you think Hachiken's
starting to crack?
ヤバい:dangerous|awful|terrific
ちょっとヤバくない　八軒
Yeah...
やっぱ:too/also|still, 枚[まい]:counter for flat objects (e.g. sheets of paper), 枚[びら, ビラ]:bill/handbill/flier, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
八軒　やっぱ１人１枚くらいはあった方がいいかな～
Hachiken, you think there should
be one pizza per person?
Pizza Travelogue
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, っぽい:-ish/-like|tossing something out
実は　無理っぽい
Actually, I don't think it's possible.
What?!
ごめん
Sorry.
簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great
簡単にできるとか大きなこと言って
I know I said it's easy and stuff.
But why?!
何でだよ
手間[てま]:time/labour/labor, ともかく:anyhow/anyway/somehow or other
手間はともかく
Labor aside,
材料[ざいりょう]:ingredients|material (for a novel, experiment, etc.)|basis (for a decision)|, 揃える[そろえる]:to collect|to arrange|to make uniform, 金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal
材料揃える金が…
I don't have the money
to get the ingredients.
Our farm lets us do whatever
we want with produce
野菜[やさい]:vegetable, 農場[のうじょう]:farm (agriculture), 規格[きかく]:standard/norm, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you, 放出[ほうしゅつ]:release/emission/ejection
野菜ならここの農場で規格外のを「ご自由に」って放出してるぞ
that isn't part of an ongoing project.
Really?!
マジで！？
We grow greenhouse tomatoes,
so we can make tomato sauce.
ハウス:house, トマト:tomato (Solanum lycopersicum), トマトソース:tomato sauce, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
ハウスにトマトもあるからトマトソース作れるな
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
俺作りたい
I want to do that!
Right, you're in Food Processing!
食品[しょくひん]:food/food products/foodstuffs, 加工[かこう]:manufacturing/processing/treatment, 科[か]:department|course (of study)|(taxonomical) family, 科[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness
おお　食品加工科
いや　待て待て
No, wait a minute.
Without flour, we have nothing—
小麦粉[こむぎこ]:wheat flour
小麦粉がなけりゃ何にも…
飼い葉[かいば]:fodder, 燕麦[えんばく, からすむぎ]:wild oat (Avena fatua)/wild oats|oat (Avena sativa), 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 産[うぶ]:innocent/naive|birth-, 産[さん]:(giving) birth|native of|assets
飼い葉や燕麦など全てエゾノー産ですよ
The same goes for the fodder and oats.
They're all grown here at Ezonoo.
Storage
Flour? Yeah, we've got our own.
小麦粉[こむぎこ]:wheat flour
小麦粉？
産[うぶ]:innocent/naive|birth-, 産[さん]:(giving) birth|native of|assets
あるぞ　エゾノー産
何ｔ使う？
How many tons do you need?
結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||
キロで結構です
Kilos, not tons!
Dairy Science
Cheese for pizza?
用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, チーズ:cheese
ピザ用チーズ？
You said your dream's
to open a cheese shop, right?
チーズ:cheese, 工房[こうぼう]:workshop/studio/atelier, 開く[ひらく]:to open|to bloom|to open (for business, e.g. in the morning)||, 開く[あく]:to open (e.g. doors)|to open (e.g. business, etc.)|to be empty||, 夢[ゆめ]:dream
吉野って　チーズ工房開くのが夢だって言ってたろ
まとまる:to be collected/to be settled/to be in order, 量[りょう]:quantity/amount/volume, 量[はか]:progress, チーズ:cheese, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
まとまった量のチーズ欲しいんだけど
I want a decent amount.
Do you think there's anything
at school that can give me that?
学校[がっこう]:school, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within
学校内のもので何とかなんねえかな
We don't really see cheese
among the school's products.
販売[はんばい, ハンバイ]:sales/selling/marketing, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, チーズ:cheese
ここの販売物ってチーズ見ないね
It's hard to age it.
熟成[じゅくせい]:maturing/ripening/aging, 難しい[むずかしい, むつかしい]:difficult|fussy|gloomy||
熟成させるのが難しいんだよ
やっぱ:too/also|still, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 工房[こうぼう]:workshop/studio/atelier, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
やっぱちゃんとした工房じゃないと作れないのか
So I guess you need proper
facilities to make it.
No, I have a hunch...
心当たり[こころあたり]:having in mind/happening to know of/idea
いや　心当たりが…
Here, see?
ほら　ここ
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, チーズ:cheese, 加工[かこう]:manufacturing/processing/treatment, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar
小さいけどチーズ加工室
It's tiny, but it's
a cheese-making room!
実習[じっしゅう]:practice/practising/training (esp. practical and hands-on), カッテージチーズ:cottage cheese, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
あぁ　ここなら実習でカッテージチーズ作るときに入ったよね
Oh, we came in here to make
cottage cheese for a practicum.
It's got way too many tools.
道具[どうぐ]:tool/implement|means, 揃う[そろう]:to become complete|to be equal|to gather, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
道具が揃い過ぎてる
本格的[ほんかくてき]:genuine|full-scale|full-fledged, チーズ:cheese, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
これなら本格的なチーズ作れるっしょ
That means this place
can make proper cheese.
Campus Building Floor Plans
Cheese Making Room
If there's a cheese making room...
加工[かこう]:manufacturing/processing/treatment, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar, 熟成[じゅくせい]:maturing/ripening/aging, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly
加工室があるってことは熟成室が必ず近くに…
the curing room must be nearby.
But, based on the floor plan,
there's not enough room for one.
図面[ずめん]:drawing/diagram/plans, スペース:space (room, area, outer space)
でも図面だとそんなスペースないよ
Livestock Management Building
Manager: Nakajima Miyuki
I see! It was in the floorspace!
床下[ゆかした]:under the floor
そっか　床下にあったんだ
Wh-Wh-What are you all doing here?!
な…何ですか　君たちは！
中島[なかじま]:island in a pond or river, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
すいません　中島先生
Sorry, Nakajima-sensei.
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, チーズ:cheese, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
ピザ作るのにどうしてもチーズ欲しくて
We just really need
cheese to make pizza.
No!
秘密[ひみつ]:secret|secret|esoteric teachings
なりません　これは秘密の…
This is my secret...
Don't go in without permission!
下りる[おりる]:to descend (e.g. a mountain)|to alight (e.g. from bus)|to step down||
下りていいかな
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily
勝手に入るなぁ！
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
お願いします　先生
Please, Sensei!
ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions, 学校[がっこう]:school, 協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration
やりたいことがあったら　学校が協力してくれるって言ったじゃないですか
You said the school would
help out if we had something
we wanted to try!
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 相談[そうだん]:consultation/discussion, なさる:to do, とも言う[ともいう]:also called
何かするときはまず先生に相談しなさいとも言ったはずです
I believe I also said you should
consult a teacher first.
Wow!
Yay! Gouda!
ゴーダチーズ:Gouda cheese
やった　ゴーダチーズだ
Can you use that for pizza?
使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
ピザに使えるのか
I read mozzarella's good for pizza...
本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess, モッツァレラ:mozzarella
本読んだら　ピザにはモッツァレラがいいって
Japanese people prefer
Gouda, so it's fine!
ゴーダ:Gouda, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 日本人[にほんじん, にっぽんじん]:Japanese person/Japanese people, 好み[このみ]:liking/taste/choice, 好み[よしみ, ぎ]:friendship/friendly relations/connection, 合う[あう, おう]:to come together|to fit|to be profitable|
ゴーダの方が日本人の好みに合ってるんだよ　大丈夫
Did you make all of these, Sensei?
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
これ全部先生が？
Only a select few know of this, okay?
一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document)
ここは一部の人間しか知らないんですからね
Please be discreet!
内密[ないみつ]:privacy/secrecy/confidentiality, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
内密にお願いしますよ
You're appropriating school property
for personal use.
学校[がっこう]:school, 備品[びひん]:fixtures/furnishings/equipment, 私物化[しぶつか]:appropriation/misappropriation/making one's own
学校の備品を私物化ですか
欲[よく]:greed/craving/desire, まみれる:to be smeared/to be covered, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
人間は欲にまみれた生き物なのです
Human beings are full of greed.
We'll keep this place a secret,
秘密[ひみつ]:secret|secret|esoteric teachings, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, チーズ:cheese, 下さる[くださる]:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
ここのこと秘密にしますんで　一番いいチーズ下さい
so give us your best cheese.
えーと:let me see/well/errr ..., 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order
えーと　次は…
Okay, next...
Hachiken is really serious about this.
やる気[やるき]:willingness (e.g. to do something)/eagerness/motivation
本当にやる気だね　八軒
I think he's studying up a storm.
勢い[いきおい]:force|influence|impetus|, 勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
すっごい勢いで勉強してるみたいよ
At first, he was reluctant, wasn't he?
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 嫌々[いやいや]:unwillingly|shaking head in refusal (to children)|no!, じゃん:isn't it
最初は嫌々だったじゃん
部活[ぶかつ]:club activities, 実習[じっしゅう]:practice/practising/training (esp. practical and hands-on), 他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 抱え込む[かかえこむ]:to hold a thing in one's arms/to carry in one's arms|to take upon oneself, じゃう:to do something completely
部活と実習の他にピザまで抱え込んじゃって
He has pizza to deal with,
on top of his club and practicums.
He even named a piglet.
子豚[こぶた]:piglet, 付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||
子豚に名前付けちゃったりさ
He's a nice guy.
お人よしだよね
You know, Hachiken's the type to
miss out because he's too nice.
あれだね
良い[よい]:good|sufficient (can be used to turn down an offer)|profitable (e.g. deal, business offer, etc.)|, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by, 損する[そんする]:to lose (money, etc.)|to have wasted one's (time, etc.)/to have one's efforts come to naught, タイプ:type/kind/sort
八軒は人が良過ぎて損するタイプだね
そうかもね
Maybe.
損[そん]:loss/damage|disadvantage
でもさ　損でも何でも
But missing out or not,
good people attract good people.
Pizza Ovens
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble
いい人の所には人が集まるよ
Crap!
ヤベッ！
I have to check whether the oven
even works in the first place!
そもそも:in the first place/to begin with|... the heck (e.g. "what the heck?"), 使[し]:messenger|police and judicial chief (Heian and Kamakura periods)|klesha (polluting thoughts such as greed, hatred and delusion, which result in suffering), 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
そもそも石窯が使いもんになるか確認しなきゃ
えーと:let me see/well/errr ..., 時半[じはん]:about an hour/short time|half past (the hour), 着[ちゃく]:counter for suits of clothing|arriving at ..., 着[ぎ]:clothes/outfit/uniform
えーと　１１時半にエゾノー前着と
Okay, arrive in front
of Ezonoo at 11:30.
Hokkaido Ooezo Agricultural High School
Ooezo Agricultural High School Motto
Defy Logic  Cooperation  Diligence
Dairy Science
疲れ[つかれ]:tiredness/fatigue
はい　お疲れ
Okay, good work.
See you guys tomorrow.
あした:morning, あした:tomorrow|near future
またあしたな
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now
最近何やってんだ　あいつ
What's he up to lately?
片付ける[かたづける]:to tidy up|to settle (problem)|to finish||
片付けてくれてたんだ
You cleaned the place up for me?
Yeah, I have some time
before club starts.
部活[ぶかつ]:club activities, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance
部活まで少し時間があるしね
I want to eat pizza, too,
so I thought I'd help out.
食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
私もピザ食べたいから何か手伝おうと思って
奇麗[きれい, キレイ]:pretty|clean|completely, かまど:kitchen range/cooking stove/hearth, 焼く[やく]:to burn|to roast|to heat||
奇麗なかまどで焼きたいもんね
We'd want to bake them
in a clean oven, right?
最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 何枚[なんまい]:how many thin flat objects?, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
最高のピザ何枚でも食わせてやるぞお
I'll let you eat the best pizza ever,
as many as you want!
Man, it's broken like I'd suspected.
やっぱ:too/also|still, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
あー　やっぱ壊れてる
I wonder if we can fix it ourselves.
素人[しろうと, しろと]:amateur|respectable woman (not a prostitute, hostess, geisha, etc.)|unlicensed prostitute, 直す[なおす]:to cure|to fix|to do over again (after -masu base of verb)||
素人でも直せるかな　これ
こんなときは…
In times like these...
I'll fix it for you.
直す[なおす]:to cure|to fix|to do over again (after -masu base of verb)||
直してやるよ
Third-Year, Agricultural Engineering Department
ゴールデンウイーク:Golden Week (early-May holiday season in Japan), 馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop, 世話[せわ]:looking after/help/aid, 代わる[かわる]:to succeed|to take the place of|to be exchanged, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
ゴールデンウイークのとき　お前に馬の世話代わってもらったしな
You swapped in for me
to take care of the horses
over Golden Week, after all!
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
ありがとうございます
Thank you!
大川[おおかわ, たいせん]:big river, 焼く[やく]:to burn|to roast|to heat||
大川さんの分もピザ焼きます
I'll bake you a pizza, too!
Oh, you'll need wood if
you're baking in an oven.
焼く[やく]:to burn|to roast|to heat||
石窯で焼くならまきいるべ
材料[ざいりょう]:ingredients|material (for a novel, experiment, etc.)|basis (for a decision)|, 廃材[はいざい]:scrap wood/scrap material, 集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather
材料の廃材集めてやろうか
Do you want me to gather
up some scrap wood?
First-Year, Forestry Science Department
Really?! That'd be really helpful!
助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped
マジで　助かる
代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ...
その代わり俺にもピザ…
In return, can I have a pizza—
Sure! I'll let you have one!
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
食わせる　食わせるよ
List of Pizza Eaters
Beppu, Nishikawa, Futamata, Kawai, Aikawa
Tamako, Nishikura, Mikage, Yoshino, Ookawa
Tamako's brother, Kino, Nakajima-Sensei
Man... I thought I could get away
with just making two or three,
枚[まい]:counter for flat objects (e.g. sheets of paper), 枚[びら, ビラ]:bill/handbill/flier, 焼く[やく]:to burn|to roast|to heat||
ああ　２～３枚焼けばいいと思ってたのに
とんでも:unthinkable/unexpected/outrageous, 枚数[まいすう]:the number of flat things|win-loss difference which influences the ranking of wrestlers
とんでもない枚数に
but now I've got to make a ton.
作り[つくり]:making|appearance (i.e. attire, make-up)|build (i.e. physique)||, 作り[づくり]:making/forming|form
作りがいあるね
That makes it worth making.
数学[すうがく]:mathematics/arithmetic, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
八軒　数学教えてくれ～
Hachiken, teach me math!
あら？
Hey, if they find you visiting other
students' rooms during study time,
学習[がくしゅう]:study/learning/tutorial, 訪問[ほうもん]:call/visit, バレる:to leak out (a secret)/to be exposed (a lie, improper behaviour, etc.) (behavior), 罰[ばち]:(divine) punishment/curse/retribution, 罰[ばつ]:punishment/penalty, 当番[とうばん]:being on duty
お前なぁ　学習時間中の他室訪問がバレたら罰当番だぞ
you'll get detention chores.
He's been working non-stop all week.
今週[こんしゅう]:this week
今週かかりっきりだったもんな
会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association, あした:morning, あした:tomorrow|near future
そっか　ピザ会あしたか
Right, the pizza party's tomorrow!
It'll be awesome.
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
楽しみだな
Sorry to bother.
邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
邪魔したな
Oh, what about math?
数学[すうがく]:mathematics/arithmetic
あれ　いいのか　数学
たまに:occasionally/once in a while, 自力[じりき, じりょく]:one's own strength/one's own efforts|self-salvation, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
たまには自力で頑張る　じゃ
I can try on my own once in a while.
See ya!
It's been a rough road,
but he got this far.
何だかんだ[なんだかんだ, なんだかだ]:something or other/one thing or another/this or that
何だかんだでここまできたねぇ
後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, ベーコン:bacon
後はピザ用のベーコンだけだってよ
I heard bacon's all that's left.
Ooezo Agricultural
High School
Ooezo Bus
Phew, what a hot day.
暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm
今日は暑いなぁ
Bacon?
ベーコン:bacon
ベーコン？
例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|
あるよ　例のピザ用だろ
Sure.
It's for the pizza, right?
We didn't sell everything,
so you can have the leftovers.
販売[はんばい, ハンバイ]:sales/selling/marketing, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, 残り[のこり]:remnant/residue/remaining, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
販売用の残り取っといたのあるから　やるよ
Thank you.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
ありがとうございます
Is this one doing okay?
順調[じゅんちょう]:favourable/favorable/doing well, 育つ[そだつ]:to be raised (e.g. child)/to be brought up/to grow (up)
順調に育ってますか　こいつ
遅れる[おくれる]:to be late/to be delayed/to fall behind schedule
うん　ちょっと遅れてるかな
Might be on the slow side.
付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||, 豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables
名前付けたんだって　豚丼
I heard you gave it a name?
Pork Bowl.
I guess that's bad, right?
やっぱ:too/also|still, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
やっぱ駄目っすかね
子豚[こぶた]:piglet, カワイイ:cute/adorable/charming
いや　子豚カワイイもんな
Nah, piglets are cute.
I can understand why
you'd want to name one.
付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
名前付けたくなる気持ち分かるよ
Food Science Department   Meat Processing Room
Meat Processing
Practicum Room
Can you eat him?
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
食えるか
When Pork Bowl becomes pork,
could you eat it?
豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables, 肉[にく, しし]:flesh|meat|the physical body (as opposed to the spirit)||
豚丼が肉にされたとき
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
食えるかって聞いてんだよ
Inada,
Yr. 3
カ月[かげつ]:months (period of), 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 子豚[こぶた]:piglet
これは３カ月前まであいつと同じ子豚だった
Three months ago, this one
was a piglet, just like him.
He will eventually become
ham and bacon, too.
いずれ:where/which|anyway, ベーコン:bacon
あいつもいずれハムやベーコンになる
When the time comes,
could you eat it?
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
その時が来たら食えるか
正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly
正直…
To be honest...
To be honest, I won't know
until the time comes.
正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly
正直そのときになってみないと分かんないです
もやもや:hazy/murky|gloomy, 答え[こたえ, いらえ]:answer/reply/response
もやもやして答え出ないっす
I'm so conflicted and
don't have an answer.
底[そこ]:bottom/sole, 底[てい]:base (logarithmic, exponential, number system)|base (triangle, cone, cylinder, etc.)|type, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, うろうろ:loiteringly/aimless wandering/restlessly, 感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression
何かいつまでたっても底の方でうろうろしてる感じで…
I feel I'm lost deep inside,
just wandering around...
If you're feeling conflicted,
もやもや:hazy/murky|gloomy
もやもやしてるってことは
出口[でぐち]:exit/gateway/way out, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
出口を探し続けているってことだ
it means you're still
looking for an answer.
身[み]:body|oneself|one's place|, 身[むくろ]:(dead) body/corpse, 体験[たいけん]:personal experience/physical experience/one's own experience
そうやって身をもって体験して
If you don't experience
that search for the answer yourself,
it won't become a part
of who you are.
出口[でぐち]:exit/gateway/way out, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, 血肉[けつにく]:flesh and blood/relatives
自分で出口を見つけないと本当の血肉にならないだろう
試食[ししょく]:sampling food
ほれ　試食
Here, have a taste.
Oh, thanks.
どうも
Aw, man...
困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
困る　何てこった
What'll I do?
Why does it have to taste so good?!
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
うまいんすよね　困ったことに
Right? Want seconds?
代わる[かわる]:to succeed|to take the place of|to be exchanged
お代わりいるか
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 勢揃い[せいぞろい]:array/muster/line-up
何で先生方が勢揃いなんですか
Why are all the teachers here, too?
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
いや　何か面白そうなことしてるな～って
Oh, it seemed like something
fun was going on.
関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full
それに関係ないやつらもいっぱいいるし
Not to mention, all these
extra people showed up, too!
部活[ぶかつ]:club activities, 連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe, 嗅ぎつける[かぎつける]:to sniff out/to get wind of, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
部活の連中が嗅ぎつけてきたらしい
Other club members found out.
Hey.
やあ
S-Shiroishi-sensei, why are you here?
白石[しろいし]:white stone|white (go pieces), 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
白石先生　何でこんなとこに
元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy
元気でやっているかなと思って
I was just wondering
how you've been doing.
おーい:hey!/oi!|I, 始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
おーい　八軒　始めるべー
Hey, Hachiken, let's start!
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
あ…それじゃ　先生　また
Oh...
Okay, later, then.
O-Okay.
お…おう
How is Hachiken-kun?
どうです　八軒君は
はらはら:to feel anxious/to feel nervous|fluttering down
はらはらしますなぁ
I'm anxious.
痛[いた]:ouch/ow/that hurt, 痛[つう]:pain/ache/-algia
痛え
Ow!
Be careful, Hachi!
気を付ける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care
気を付けろ　ハチ
しゃべる:to talk/to chat/to chatter, 注目[ちゅうもく]:notice/attention/observation
おっ　八軒がしゃべるぞ　注目
Hey, Hachiken's gonna speak! Attention!
Uh, today is excellent
weather for baking pizza—
本日[ほんじつ]:today, 日柄[ひがら]:lucky or unlucky aspect of a given day, 良い[よい]:good|sufficient (can be used to turn down an offer)|profitable (e.g. deal, business offer, etc.)|
本日はお日柄も良く…
前置き[まえおき]:preface/introduction/preamble
前置きいいから
Forget the speech!
Just bake pizzas already!
焼ける[やける]:to burn/to be roasted|to be jealous
はよピザ焼け！
Yeah!
分かったよ
Fine!
火[ひ]:fire/flame/blaze, 火[か]:Tuesday|fire (second of the five elements), 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, 高温[こうおん]:high temperature, 維持[いじ]:maintenance/preservation/improvement
石窯には２時間前から火を入れて高温を維持してあります
The oven has been going for two hours
and has reached high temperatures.
The agricultural engineering
department helped fix the oven,
窯[かま]:stove/furnace/kiln, 修理[しゅうり, しゅり]:repairing/mending/servicing, 土木[どぼく]:engineering works/civil engineering/public works, 科[か]:department|course (of study)|(taxonomical) family
なお　窯の修理は土木科
森林[しんりん]:forest/woods, 科[か]:department|course (of study)|(taxonomical) family, 科[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
まきは森林科に協力してもらいました
and the forestry department
helped acquire firewood.
The flour for the dough was grown
by the agricultural sciences department,
生地[きじ]:cloth|one's true character|unglazed pottery|, 生地[せいち]:birthplace, 小麦粉[こむぎこ]:wheat flour, 農業[のうぎょう]:agriculture, 科[か]:department|course (of study)|(taxonomical) family, 科[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 栽培[さいばい]:cultivation
生地の小麦粉は農業科で栽培し
食品[しょくひん]:food/food products/foodstuffs, 科[か]:department|course (of study)|(taxonomical) family, 科[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 製粉[せいふん]:milling/grinding into flour
食品科で製粉したものです
and milled by the food
processing department.
The dough's spread with tomato paste.
トマトペースト:tomato paste, 塗る[ぬる]:to paint/to plaster/to lacquer
トマトペーストを塗って
The bacon was made by the
food processing department,
ベーコン:bacon, 酪農[らくのう]:dairy (farm), 科[か]:department|course (of study)|(taxonomical) family, 科[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 育てる[そだてる]:to raise|to train|to promote the growth of, 豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 食品[しょくひん]:food/food products/foodstuffs, 加工[かこう]:manufacturing/processing/treatment
ベーコンは酪農科が育てた豚を食品科が加工
using pigs raised by the
dairy science department.
The vegetables used for toppings
載せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||, 野菜[やさい]:vegetable, 農業[のうぎょう]:agriculture, 科[か]:department|course (of study)|(taxonomical) family, 科[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 栽培[さいばい]:cultivation
上に載せる野菜は農業科で栽培
were grown by the agricultural
sciences department...
Wait, the vegetables aren't here.
野菜[やさい]:vegetable
あれ　野菜来てない
They're not?
来てない！？
担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.)
担当西川だよな
Wasn't Nishikawa responsible for them?
うーっす
Yo.
You're late, Nishikawa!
遅えよ　西川
Complain after the meal's over!
文句[もんく]:complaint/grumbling|phrase, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
文句は食い終わってから聞こう
Behold the tastiness of
freshly picked produce!
取れる[とれる]:to come off|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear|to be caught||, 野菜[やさい]:vegetable, うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 思い知る[おもいしる]:to realize/to realise
取れたて野菜のうまさを思い知れ
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, チーズ:cheese, 載せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
えー　最後にチーズを載せまして
Lastly, we add a layer of cheese.
酪農[らくのう]:dairy (farm), 科[か]:department|course (of study)|(taxonomical) family, 科[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration, 入手[にゅうしゅ]:acquisition/obtaining/coming to hand
と…これは酪農科の吉野さんのご協力で入手しました
Uh, the cheese was obtained
with help from Yoshino-san
in dairy science.
窯[かま]:stove/furnace/kiln, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, 約[やく]:approximately|promise|shortening|
これを窯に入れて約５分です
We put them in the oven and bake
for approximately five minutes.
It's about done, right?
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon
そろそろだろ
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 焼ける[やける]:to burn/to be roasted|to be jealous
ちゃんと焼けてるのかな　これ
Is this cooked properly?
Okay, you do the taste test.
毒味[どくみ]:poison tasting/foretaste
んじゃ　八軒が毒味
Thanks for the food.
いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
いただきます
Wh-What's wrong?
ど…どうしたの
Did Hachiken lose it?
壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
八軒　壊れた？
デリシャス:delicious
デリシャス
Wow, what is this?
ちょっと何これ
It's so tasty, it makes you laugh!
笑える[わらえる]:to be made to laugh, うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious
笑えるうまさだ
Bake on!
焼ける[やける]:to burn/to be roasted|to be jealous, 次々[つぎつぎ]:in succession/one by one
焼け　焼け　次々焼け！
Bake non-stop!
Dual-wielding pizza!
二刀流[にとうりゅう]:two-sword school|liking both alcohol and sweets|bisexuality|
ピザ二刀流だ～い！
The veggies are delicious!
野菜[やさい]:vegetable, おいしい:delicious/tasty|attractive
野菜おいしい
Asparagus go downhill really
fast the moment you pick them,
アスパラ:asparagus, 瞬間[しゅんかん]:moment/second/instant, 鮮度[せんど]:(degree of) freshness, ずんずん:rapidly (e.g. progress, moving forward)/growing visibly/quickly, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||
アスパラはとった瞬間から鮮度がずんずん落ちるからな
so speed is important.
スピード:speed, 勝負[しょうぶ]:victory or defeat/match/contest
スピード勝負だ
Where's this cheese from?
It's super tasty.
チーズ:cheese
これどこのチーズ
めちゃくちゃ:absurd/unreasonable|extreme, おいしい:delicious/tasty|attractive
めちゃくちゃおいしいんだけど
That's a secret.
ひ　み　つ！
Yum...
うまる:to be buried/to be covered|to overflow
うまっ
取り仕切る[とりしきる]:to operate a business/to run a business/to manage all by oneself, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
これ八軒が取り仕切って作ったのか
Did Hachiken organize all this?
埋まる[うまる, うずまる]:to be buried|to overflow|to be repaid (e.g. debt), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
こんなにいいものがごみに埋まってたなんてねー
Who knew that something so useful
would be buried in trash?
完全[かんぜん]:perfection/completeness, 趣味[しゅみ]:hobby/pastime|tastes, 窯[かま]:stove/furnace/kiln
これ完全に趣味の窯でしょ
This oven was totally for
someone's hobby, wasn't it?
I wonder who made it.
造る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
誰が造ったんですかね
Oops.
ぎくっ！
Ah, this makes you want a beer.
ビール:beer, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
いやぁ　これはビールが欲しくなりますね
Shall we make Ezonoo beer?!
造る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
造りますか　エゾノービール
高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, ビール:beer, 造る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
でも高校でビールを造るってのは…
But, making beer at a high school?
いやいや:no!/no no!/no, not at all, いやいや:unwillingly/grudgingly|shaking head in refusal (to children), 日本酒[にほんしゅ]:sake/Japanese rice wine, 造る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
いやいや　日本酒を造ってる高校もあるくらいですから
Oh, but there are even
high schools that make sake.
We can set up a fermentation
and brewing science course...
発酵[はっこう]:fermentation/zymosis, 醸造[じょうぞう]:brewing/distillation, 学[がく]:-ology/-ics|learning, 授業[じゅぎょう]:lesson/class work/teaching
発酵醸造学として授業を…うん？
Ooezo Agricultural High School
Pizza Festival
Plan
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best
どうせなら
Why not make this an
event open to the public?
会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association, 一般人[いっぱんじん]:ordinary person/member of the general public/non-celebrity, 巻き込む[まきこむ]:to roll up/to enfold|to involve, イベント:event
このピザ会を一般人も巻き込んだイベントにしてみては
We can charge entrance fees!
入場料[にゅうじょうりょう]:entrance fee/admission fee/admission, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
入場料を取って
Yum!
うまる:to be buried/to be covered|to overflow
うまっ
Man, I'm exhausted.
疲れる[つかれる]:to get tired|to be worn out (e.g. of well used objects)|to starve
疲れた～
今週[こんしゅう]:this week, 丸々[まるまる]:plump/rotund|entirely
今週丸々使っちゃったな
I used up the entire week...
Good job!
お疲れさま[おつかれさま]:thank you/many thanks|that's enough for today
お疲れさま
We can finally take a breather.
やっと:at last/at length|barely, 一息[ひといき]:one breath|one go (i.e. in a short time)|small amount of effort
やっと一息つけたね
Here's some tea.
茶[ちゃ]:tea|tea plant (Camellia sinensis)|tea preparation||, どうぞ:please/kindly|by all means
お茶どうぞ
It was super yummy and fun!
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), おいしい:delicious/tasty|attractive, 楽しい[たのしい]:enjoyable/fun
すごくおいしくてすごく楽しかった
Thanks!
ありがと:Thank you
ありがと
Oh. Um, thanks for helping.
いや…まあ…
手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to, ありがと:Thank you
手伝ってくれてありがとな
疲れ[つかれ]:tiredness/fatigue
お疲れ～
Good job!
What're you doing?!
何すんだ
It was yummy!
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious
うまかった
It was fun!
W-Wait... Stop! Stop!
ありがと:Thank you
ありがとな
ストップ:stop
ちょ…ちょっと…ストップ　ストップ　スト…
St...
Who added milk?!
牛乳[ぎゅうにゅう]:(cow's) milk, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
誰だ！？　牛乳入れたの！
エゾノーブレンド
Call it the Ezonoo blend.
Who'd drink this?!
飲める[のめる]:to be able to drink|to be worth drinking
飲めるか　こんなの
中学生[ちゅうがくせい]:junior high school student/middle school pupil
中学生のころの八軒は
In junior high, Hachiken seemed to be
いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good, 思い[おもい]:thought|imagination|desire||, 縛る[しばる]:to tie/to bind
「何かにならなきゃいけない」という思いに縛られて
held hostage by the thought that he
had to make something of himself,
so much so, that he had no idea
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), すっぽり:entirely/completely|cleanly, 抜ける[ぬける]:to come out|to fade|to wear a hole (e.g. clothes)||
「どんな人間になりたいか」がすっぽり抜けていたように思います
what kind of person he wanted to be.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), つかめる:to seize/to catch|to obtain
こちらなら　何かつかめるのではないかと思って
I sent him your way,
thinking he might gain some insight.
放り込む[ほうりこむ]:to throw into/to toss into
放り込んでみたのですが
Was my hunch correct?
正解[せいかい]:correct/right/correct interpretation (answer, solution)
正解でしたかな
まだまだ:still some way to go before the goal/still more to come/much more
どうなるかまだまだ分かりませんよー
We still have to wait and see.
But, it seems that he has gained
some insight today, at least.
けれど
少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce, つかめる:to seize/to catch|to obtain
少なくとも今日は何かをつかめたようですよ
さて
Now...
All right, everyone!
諸君[しょくん]:you (people)|gentlemen/ladies and gentlemen
はーい　諸君
楽しむ[たのしむ]:to enjoy (oneself), 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 片付け[かたづけ]:tidying up/finishing
楽しんだ後は片付けですよ
Now that you've had fun,
it's cleanup time!
後日[ごじつ, ごにち]:in the future/another day/later, 食料[しょくりょう]:food, 自給[じきゅう]:self-support, リポート:report/paper, 提出[ていしゅつ]:to present/to submit (e.g. a report or a thesis)|presentation
そして　後日　食料自給についてのリポート提出
I expect a report on food
self-sufficiency from each of you!
え～！
Good experiences should
lead to good learning!
良い[よい]:good|sufficient (can be used to turn down an offer)|profitable (e.g. deal, business offer, etc.)|, 経験[けいけん]:experience, 勉学[べんがく]:study/pursuit of knowledge, 生かす[いかす]:to make (the best) use of|to let live|to revive
良い経験をしたら勉学に生かしましょ
たまに:occasionally/once in a while, 手紙[てがみ]:letter, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
たまには手紙を書いてみようよ
ポストカード:postcard, でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
どっかにポストカードでもあったけ
懐かしい[なつかしい]:dear/desired/missed, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
懐かしい顔に見けて
ほんの:mere/only/just, 数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|, ノスタルジー:nostalgia
ほんの数行ノスタルジーを
調子[ちょうし]:tune|vein|condition||
調子はどうですか
忙しい[いそがしい, せわしい]:busy/occupied|restless, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
忙しくしていますか
無我夢中[むがむちゅう]:being absorbed in/losing oneself in, 探しまわる[さがしまわる]:to search about for/to hunt around for/to look high and low for
無我夢中で探しまわってた
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 具合[ぐあい]:condition/state/manner, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.)
あの夢の具合はどんなだい
気分転換[きぶんてんかん]:change of pace/change of mood/(mental) break (e.g. going for a walk), くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
気分転換くらいのノリで
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 歌う[うたう]:to sing|to sing (one's praises in a poem, etc.)/to compose a poem
一緒に歌わないか
無我夢中[むがむちゅう]:being absorbed in/losing oneself in, 探しまわる[さがしまわる]:to search about for/to hunt around for/to look high and low for
そして無我夢中で探しまわってた
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 続き[つづき]:sequel/continuation/(also suffix) continuation (in time and space), 語り合う[かたりあう]:to talk together
あの夢の続きを語り合おうよ
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
明日は頑張ろうぜ
未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
今はそこにある未来へ
駆け出す[かけだす]:to run off/to break into a run/to start running
駆け出して さぁ 行こう
This story is a work of fiction.
The people and groups are fictitious, but the themes relating to food and life are firmly based in reality. Visiting the places and facilities used as models can be dangerous and may result it contracting diseases from the animals. Please enjoy this story as a work of fiction.